so there's a question on dealing with
sensuality and lust in particular
and
this is uh when
in mind affected with lust is active
i try my best not to give in
by having cold showers exercising
breath counting meditation and other
activities such as avoidance of
perceptions that inflame the last
further when enough time passes the active lust
when enough time passes the active lust
is gone but the lust is still present in
that dormant sense
i have not cured the last but i've dealt
with some of its symptoms
so then what is the cause of lust
or what is last a symptom of
the cause of lust is being activated
from its dormant state
um seems to me
seems to be me carelessly attending to
lasting flame perceptions
but then even if i'm careful still lust
is there waiting in the background
pressuring me to activate it
such awareness and restraint are quite
exhausting and the only way i know how
to relax is by doing the very thing i'm
not trying to do which is to activate
lust so what should i do
so what should i do
so yes sense restraint not acting out of
lust not aggravating the situation further
not aggravating the situation further
as i say often that's the first step all
the other things that are done here that
are described here
are kind of on the level of management
of lust which obviously that is obvious
to this person
and the real problem of lust is the that
the real problem of lust is the that
fact that it's um
that dormant state how it refers to so
it's kind of the possibility of lust is
uh always present
and that's where the buddha said
like it's not enough to just not have
last present in your mind throughout the
day and so on
you also need to keep reviewing your
mind and questioning it in a sense that
you want to see whether non-arisen
central lust can arise
because if you're unsure about the answer means
if you're unsure about the answer means
it can so doubt means yes it can arise
as this person asks what should i do so
how can i then
having dealt with particular
manifestations of lust endured them not
actually distracting myself from it and
so on as long as i didn't act out of it
so now when the mind is free from those
particular manifestations of lust
how do i then deal with that dormant
possibility of last manifesting and
pressuring me
and the answer is when the mind is free
from the particular you know engagements
or preoccupations with last
and if it's not free you have to
basically endure it through the sense
restraint until it comes down and it
will have to come down
so when it comes down temporarily
then you need to make the effort to
contemplate the danger
in those things that you're currently
free from those particular
uh infatuations with with with sense uh
pleasures and so on
uh because as long as the danger is
doesn't become apparent uh the dormant
lust will still be your framework so in
other words you will be within the
dormant last that it's waiting to be
activated you won't be stepping outside
of its domain in other words you won't
be free
uh you won't be um
in that like you won't you want you
won't be safe to put it that way and uh
it is a question of safety
because uh as you know various suitors
describe the whole purpose of central pleasures
the whole purpose of central pleasures
and the last the insight and so on
through carelessly attending to them
is to to trap you it's a it's a trap
it's a bait
uh it's a it's a like a fish hook that
you don't see
it then keeps you bound to pretty much
everything else that burdens you and
overwhelms you and makes your life
unpleasant including like you know the future
including like you know the future
possibilities and liabilities to
sufferings and so on
so the true freedom then comes from not
being pressured by even by the
possibilities of lust so
by not having the doorman last waiting
to be activated
and so it's not a matter of choice you
can just decide to not activate the
doorman last you have to have beforehand
been developed in sense restraint virtue
seeing the dangerousness it's also a
certain mode of behavior
uh of course emotive behavior has been
kind of become your norm
that old adc implies that you have
developed a degree of proper
collectedness and watchfulness so so
you're not forgetting that you're not
supposed to give in to lust you're not
lapsing you're not ignoring it you're
sustaining that context
you're sustaining the pretty much
the reasons why you want to be free from
last you don't forget that that actually
you already got some idea
that it is better to be free from
particular lust and normal loss that
it's better to be free from pressure of
the sense desires than to engage with
them but of course when they pressure
you you forget
uh your goals to put it that way and
then you just you know go against them
so
once you kind of have been developed in
terms of your behavior in terms of not
acting out of lust
uh not not giving in in those course
modes they will be against the precepts
then as i said when the mind is not
actively gripped by lust you have to
really make the effort
and just day in day out contemplate the
danger of it
so
what would be
those you know traps those baits what are they
you know traps those baits what are they
what are those dangers
of
engaging with sense pleasures that you
know seemingly harm no one like
people enjoy them you're not causing
anybody anyone else pain and so on
you're just
just enjoying sense desires
yet the buddha said there is an inherent
danger um
um
the perception of danger that hasn't
been developed and regarded because
there is an inherited bait inherent
poison it had a trap all these things
and if you were to see that
then the most refined central pleasure
the most refined central pleasure
doesn't matter or on what level or scale
will be all seen equally as
parallel unwanted painful burning
pressuring uh pretty much everything
else that you want to avoid
so it's the contemplation of danger and
then so now you want to ask yourself so
what do i
where do i look for that danger
like what would they look at in my body
look at incense objects
where is that danger and that's why the
contemplation of danger
kind of follows after
the the correct thorough understanding of
the correct thorough understanding of
what actual gratification is
so
that's why understanding
the gratification the danger and the
escape in regard to sense desires in
regard to one's lust will free you from
it
so you you don't have to necessarily
just chronologically follow disorder you
know sometimes the danger will be
clearer sometimes the gratification will
be clear either way whichever way you
put uh forward you will be kind of uh
uh forward you will be kind of uh
understanding the the everything else
that's included in it so if you're
correctly understanding the danger of
sensuality you are then understanding uh
gratification along the right lines if
you're correctly understanding where
gratification is you are understanding
the danger on the
along the right lines so that's really
where the work is it's not about like
constantly calming these and desires and
calming and that's just as i said
management it's when
you have space to think about them when
you when you're not just completely
pressured constantly pressured
then you can actually um
make that effort that's where the
practice is to contemplate do you
understand what gratification of
synthesize is what is so
say you have a you have a desire to i
don't know eat something agreeable so
you're not hungry but there is something
that that's pressuring you to taste it
let's put it that way what would
gratification be in that instance
well the principle of gratification be
behind that instance so that you can
understand it in every instance
so if you want to taste something what
part of that experience is the
gratification is the gratification when you're
is the gratification when you're
actually putting the food in your mouth
is the gratification once you feel the
taste and you're chewing it or has the
gratification begun even in your
perception of that which is wanted and
that it's pressuring you
so on what level
you need to basically
learn how to be mindful
and not lose sight of
in order to recognize what the actual
gratification is
because the common assumption is or
gratification is once i get the thing
then i'm gratified then my desires are
satisfied and so on but that's not what
it would have said the gratification in
centrality has nothing to do with you
getting in touch with sensuality
touching it tasting it smelling it
looking at it the gratification is on
the level of delighting already at the
thought of it
so your mental elation
inspiration um
um
kind of uplifting towards uh the sense
the sense object that's already your
gratification that's already where the
danger is
everything else is secondly you haven't
even tasted that that thing you want to
taste so you just saw it
you presume
that it tastes nice on the basis of its
look and the smell and so on so now
you're craving for its taste but you are
not actually tasting it
yet your mouth is already reacting
uh you're fully gripped by the desire as
if you are fully already connected with
that desirable yet the object of your
desire remains in the world untouched
so the body is getting
agitated and aroused and and sort of
prepped for engaging with sense objects
without even engaging with sense objects
so if gratification were truly on the
level of sense objects that would not be
possible you would not be able
to get all these reactions in the body
as a result of desire unless you have
already touched and contacted the thing
that's containing the gratification so
since you're not tasting it not touching
it not not looking at it even yet here
you are
gripped by the desire and already
feeling elated on account of it and
and now you just want to go for it so to
speak so then you realize that what is
commonly assumed is gratification it's
really the result
of already of mind already gripped by
the gratification that's why
gratification is insatiable because if
you if you take it at face value
the the delight in the prospect of
central pleasures that's it your
gratification has begun and that's why
it has no end because the framework of
your mind that wants gratification the
delight sorry your mind the one central
pleasure the delights in it that's the
framework of gratification and you agree
by it and you can't fill that in so it
doesn't matter how much you're engaging
with things the framework remains
unchanged and it's forcing and
pressuring you to engage
so that's it for as long as you look for
the danger of sensuality on the level of
the actual objects you won't find it
you need to look at the level of your
delight and your inspiration
towards sense objects like and again uh you
sense objects like and again uh you
would start seeing that if you then make
the effort and practice sense restraint
then you would see how much the mind
jumps even just in the mere prospect at
a mere thought an image of
central pleasures why because
fundamentally the value
the value
of um
experiencing sense pleasures
is not seen as harmful
it's not seen as as
as a death as a dot as a pain all the
things that the buddha listed
for as long as you don't see
that value of your mental relation to
word sense pleasures if you don't see
that as the root of the danger
you will be the victim of it in other
words you would be basically acting out
of it and putting the sense objects that
are truly just second as first as the
root of the problem while the actual
root of the problem remains invisible
and then same
because see you you think the problem is
on the level of sense objects then you
try to counter and look at the sense
objects you don't want the the beautiful
the ugly hoping that will cancel the
beautiful but then you just end up being
equally attracted elated
wanting to further gratify the ugly
because any sense object basically just
starts serving the purpose of the
framework of gratification that you're
still very much holding on to uh and
fueling through your careless attention
careless attention means uh
putting the first putting second is
first and first and second that's what i
only saw
uh
the the wise attention the proper
attention means seeing things in the
right order
seeing first is first and second and
second that's where it's a necessary
prerequisite for the right view ion is
so means basically attending wrongly
attending that which is second as the
first as the reason
but it will in numerous occasions said
that um sense objects beautiful sense objects
um sense objects beautiful sense objects
are not
a desire are not sensuality in the world
it's man's desire and lust his thoughts
of desire and lust that's why there is
sensuality in regard to beautiful things
in the world he the tower has freed
himself from such thoughts
such elations such delights
he freed himself from gratification
through understanding the danger of it
thus for him beautiful things just
remain standing in the world but there
is no desire there in
um
so that's the contemplation
you need to understand what
gratification is you need to start
discerning that mental delight which is the
that mental delight which is the
background pretty much
of your experience when you're gripped
by the senses
uh by the prospect of the pleasure see
that delight is not there as the object
of what you're doing that's your state
of mind so yes you you might be
attracted by sight sound smell taste
touches but you actually recognize peripherally
but you actually recognize peripherally
oh is there an elation in my mind at the
thought of a pleasing sight that's the
danger that's what i must not welcome
further delight
except act out of
sight sounds multi-status then become
truly seen in the right place as
secondly of course first you need to
restrain in regard to those as i keep
repeating because unless you're restrained in
because unless you're restrained in
regards to side sound smell taste
touches you're not gonna see what's
peripheral to them because you don't
even see them and you don't see them
because at the slightest touch of the
pressure you act towards them
so but you know we're presupposing that
that's that has been developed
and sustained and protected
then actually you can get to recognize
that it's that mental elation that zeal
that's when in pali the word for desire
chanda is often used for zeal just in
general a good zeal
in a way
um so you have this any any like a zeal
to a word sense object sense objects to
to that you can gain the pleasure from
yeah that's basically what that what
that lust what that desire is
and uh
that delight that the buddha talks about
and that's
something you have to become familiar
and discern even before it takes over
you and it on that level you will be able to
and it on that level you will be able to
then see the danger then the dangers
would say we become apparent
because the danger are not the objects
that's why no matter how much you tr how
hard you're trying to see the danger in
the object it's always kind of secondary
it's always going to last for a while
but then it expires it doesn't really
fit with it it doesn't really apply
because that's not what it's supposed to
apply the danger is on the level of the
the danger is on the level of the
gratification so once you start
understanding what the actual
gratification of sensuality is
you then get to see her that's the
danger that's the bait that's the trap
that's the matter if i just keep
an eye
on that level and not allow
my mind to jump jump at the prospect of
elation at the prospect of that central
zeal and delight i'm safe nothing else
that used to follow can before me is
just impossible
and the clearer that becomes then the
clearer the danger of accepting it
becomes as well and then you fully
understood the escape too
see the escape it means protecting that
mind that uh so to not jump at the prospect
that uh so to not jump at the prospect
of zeal delight uh
acceptance inspiration towards central
pleasures and
and
if you protect it
you will be free eventually how long it
will take depends how much you were
dependent on those central pleasures but
eventually you will be free from that
pressure because that pressure actually
pressure centrality essentiality in
itself requires fueling requires you
accepting requires that zeal renewing
each time sort of
when you choose to give in and kind of
you know
let it run its course until you can get
to squeeze all the pleasure out that you
can from from things that did inside you
uh but see that's the fuel that then
perpetuates perpetual pressure makes it
hot makes it stronger makes it um sort
of harder to see because it increases
the burden of it so you you know your
perspective is basically shrinking the
more you give into sensuality
the harder it will be to give it up
later on same like with any other
addiction so
so
understanding the gratification
that is on the level of delight in
sensuality whether you engage with it or
not that's that secondary
the delight means you're already trapped
and then
seeing that exactly the light means i'm
already trapped means oh that's the
danger so if you understand the gratification
so if you understand the gratification
you are understanding the danger then by
being mindful of the danger you will not
set your foot in the trap and that's how
you escape the trap so understanding
danger understanding gratification
danger in the escape in regard to
sensuality will completely remove any
basis for for further fueling of of your
sense of your dependence on sensual pleasures
of your dependence on sensual pleasures
and then you will be free from it and
then there will be no more dormant
things lying around there
because again you you cease to feel them
and they would have faded away does
those dormant possibilities of engaging
with lust doesn't matter how subtle how
dormant they are fundamentally
the you only you can only engage with
them through through
mental zeal
acceptance inspiration delight welcoming of such
inspiration delight welcoming of such
thoughts
that's your gratification and if you
lose mindfulness in regard to it that's
how these dormant things become
activated so
um
hence again go back to the uh the the
sense restraint seeing that the engine
is full watchfulness i recollectedness
recognizing like
oh okay i'm free from lust now but
can last arise in me
later on today or tomorrow can things
become activated
as as the original question says
and would i know like how to how to
deactivate it so and again that's
another thing that we would say do i
know how to um
prevent non-origin loss from arising or
how to make the original lies this
allows to disappear
because again
the risen lust
doesn't need to
run its course before it disappears the
origin last is activated
because you plugged it in
let's say like that it's active because
it's plugged in plugged into what into
your framework of delight and
gratification of your zeal of your value of the
of your zeal of your value of the
pleasure that's what gives it life keeps
it active keeps it alive keeps it
pressuring you so at any given time
theoretically at least you can see
that that's the root of the problem and
that that's the danger and by seeing
that you have unplugged it
and then the whatever pressuring
sense objects that were pressuring you
with lust will be just seen as just
objects matter form perceptions and so
on the work then
is on the level of
not just sort of constantly like calming
your mind calming your mind calming your
mind calming your mind because that
pretty much requires the disturbance in
order to calm it and disturbs and gets
this calm so it's only calming your mind
it's just managing it
not uprooting it
the work is when you are
sufficiently calm when i say that and by
that i mean when you have enough space
to stop and think about it when you're
not just bombarded by some smell taste
touches then the actual work is thinking about
then the actual work is thinking about
it
making the effort to not just discern
this uh gratification and inspiration and
uh gratification and inspiration and
zeal and delight once or twice no
hundreds of times just keep doing it
keep discerning and if it's clear then
sustain that clarity keep that context
key okay so now it's great this is my
gratification because if it's clear
means you're mindful of it
means now you don't need to think about
it directly because now you're clear
that it's your relation that's where the
gratification is so there is another
issue now there is no election now you
go about your day elation pops up you
will immediately see it you will
immediately see the manifestation of a
trap the danger will be immediately
the danger will be immediately
recognized and that's enough i must know
you don't need to get rid of the trap
see in order to get rid of the trap
you'll be reaching for a trap and get
trapped the whole point is as they would often
the whole point is as they would often
say numerous suitors is to learn how to
basically go around the trap not engage
with things that will trap you
not not eat the food that contains the
bait doesn't mean you you mustn't look good
doesn't mean you you mustn't look good
smell or taste or touch anything else
but it's that
gratification and delight
and zeal and inspiration that's debate
so that pretty much then determines
whether you should engage with things or
not because again something externally might
because again something externally might
not necessarily be um
against the precepts
like like for example yeah so eating
eating something that you want to taste
is not against the precepts if it's
within the right time
but you're fully like
oriented with that
gratification and zeal towards it and
that's why you shouldn't do it not
because an object in itself is good or
bad it's because now it is rooted in
clear furthering of my already gripping
furthering of my already gripping
gripped mind by gratification and uh and
that delight and zeal and welcoming and
i want it so you are now
fully activated
um in that state of lust and that's why
it's a problem and that's why you
shouldn't do it and instead contemplate
the danger not in the cake or whatever
you want to eat but the danger in the
state of an
mind affected with that desirous zeal
that's the danger that's the trap that's
the framework again repeating the same
then on another occasion you might not
have that present at all
it's just it's still factually agreeable
taste you still factually want to eat it but
you still factually want to eat it but
there is no zeal and how do you know
that well you know that if you don't eat
it not your mental composure will not
change if something would happen to it
if you were to give it away if somebody
else did it nothing would change
internally so there is no zeal there is no
so there is no zeal there is no
inspiration there is no there is no
chanda towards it and
then you can eat it because you're not
acting out of desire